Guide to the E. Malcolm Carroll Papers, circa 1930-1954
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
E. Malcolm Carroll papers circa 1930-1954
University Archives, Duke University
Carroll, Eber Malcolm, 1893-1959.
3.7 Linear Feet 600 Items
E. Malcolm Carroll was a professor of History at Duke University from 1933-1959.
The collection includes his writings, research notes, some course materials and a manuscript, mostly undated. The collection ranges in date from circa circa 1930-1954.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The E. Malcolm Carroll Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1961.
Biographical Note
Eber Malcolm Carroll was born in 1893 in Coldwater, Michigan. He attended the University of Michigan, where he received his B.A., M.A. and Ph.D. in 1916, 1917 and 1922, respectively. From 1917-1919, he served in the U.S. Army Ambulance Service. Carroll came to Duke in 1933 to teach in the History Department. He served as chair of the Department from 1954 until his retirement in 1959. His specialties included Germany during the two World Wars, origins of the Whig Party, and French foreign affairs. From 1946-1949, he served as Deputy Editor of the German War Documents Project of the State Department which sought to uncover Nazi war schemes. He also held key posts with the Office of Strategic Services in World War II, with the rank of lieutenant colonel and was an overseas veteran of World War I. He died in December 1959 while living in the Netherlands. His books Germany and the Great Powers, 1866-1914, Soviet Communism and Western Opinion and Origins of the Whig Party were published posthumously.
Collection Overview
Collection includes manuscripts, clippings, course materials, and handwritten research notes relating to Carroll’s publishing project on German World War I and World War II documents. There is also a book-length manuscript entitled "The Western Powers and Soviet Russia, 1917-1921," a book review for the South Atlantic Quarterly, five addresses, and a copy of the preliminary bibliography of the writings of Dr. Carroll, which was compiled by Frederic B. M. Hollyday. While most items are undated, the collection ranges in date from circa circa 1930-1954.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Carroll, E. Malcolm, 1893-1959.
Hollyday, Frederic B. M.
Duke University -- History -- 20th century.
Duke University. Dept. of History.
Duke University. Dept. of History -- Faculty.
Germany -- Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Hollyday (Frederic B. M.) Papers, 1943-1971.
University Archives, Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Trinity College Historical Society, [1492?]-1981.
University Archives, Duke University.
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 4 Boxes
  - Clippings, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1954
  - Frederic Hollyday: "Printed Writings of Eber Malcolm Carroll: A Preliminary Bibliography," undated
  - Carroll's Writings:
    - "FDR and the World Crisis"
    - "Germany and the World Crisis"
    - "Germany Reviews Her History," 1952
    - "History and America's Cultural Relations with Europe"
    - "The Nature of the U.S.-U.S.S.R. Crisis"
    - "The Western Powers and Soviet Russia," Chapters I-X, edited by Hollyday
    - "What Is To Be Done About Germany?"
  - World War II Research Notes (Box 2)
  - Post-World War I Research Notes
  - World War I Research Notes
  - World War I Research Notes (Box 3)
  - World War I-World War II Research Notes
  - History 217-218 Materials, undated
  - News Clippings Related to Research, 1940
  - Manuscript: The Russian Powers and Soviet Russia, undated (Oversize 4)
  - Notebook, 1946